What are side effects of radiation?
The side effects of radiation
vary depending on what part of your body
is receiving treatment.
There are separate videos
that will go into the specific side
effects of each body side and cancer type,
as well as how to manage and reduce
the symptoms of these side effects.
On a more holistic level, individuals
undergoing radiation may experience fatigue,
such as feeling more tired or
needing a nap when they didn't before.
Some individuals are able
to continue their daily routine,
such as going to work,
keeping up with exercise, or going out
while others may need to decrease
their activity level temporarily.
These symptoms are not permanent
and should start to get better with time
after completing treatment.
Some people may have questions
about the long term effects of radiation,
such as the risk of causing
another cancer in the future.
Our modern methods of delivering
radiation are very precise,
allowing us to shape the radiation
beam to target only the tumor and reducing
as much as possible the radiation dose
to the surrounding healthy organs.
The risk of developing a secondary cancer
from treatment is very low, less than 1%,
and usually takes 15
plus years to develop.
For example, children
receiving radiation are at a higher
risk than individuals
in the latter decades of life.
Additionally, the risk on your health
of declining radiation
treatment to treat the cancer
now is much more dangerous
than the risk of getting another
cancer in 10 to 20 years.